Cool.
So thanks so much,
everyone for coming.
I think you have a
pretty cool course here.
And thanks, of course, Percy,
for inviting me to give a talk.
So I think in this class, you're
mostly talking about training
and how to train these language
models, and get to this place
where we can have these
things that can talk back to.
And today, I'm going
to talk a little bit
about once you have one of
those models, what it looks
like from the other side, what
it looks like to actually serve
these models, do inference,
turn these things from say,
electricity, into tokens,
into intelligence.
And also what are some of
the fun research problems
and research things that
you can do when you look
at it from that standpoint.
I'll start with some of
high level motivation.
I think one thing that's become
abundantly clear to all of us
is that we are really
going through almost
a new industrial
revolution in terms
of these models and
their capabilities.
These slides I made during
my job talks two years ago.
So the exact examples are
going to be pretty old,
but you can do human-level text
generation, code generation,
Cursor, Claude Code,
GPT 5.5, not just 4.
You can generate
images and videos
or understand images and
videos and process them.
You can start to
understand new modalities.
So we're starting to see
some of the applications
and the sciences in bio
and health DNA models,
all these sorts of things.
One of the things
that has really
been driving my
research for a while
is the question of what has
made these advances possible,
and how can we improve on
them in the next generations?
And one abundant driver of these
capabilities is really scale.
So again, this is
at this point, are
pretty old figure but these
models have really scaled up
in massive ways.
So in 2018, at the beginning
of my PhD in antiquity,
these were hundreds
million parameter models
at their largest.
And we were like, oh my God,
these things are pretty crazy.
By 2019, we thought that they
were too dangerous to release,
that's GPT 2.
I think in this class, you can
train a GPT 2 quality model.
I'm not sure if you did.
If you tried hard
enough, you could.
And today, of course, you
have open source models
that are a trillion
parameters and more.
Frontier is probably at 5
to 10 trillion parameters.
It's pretty exciting.
With these, you have a bunch
of new capabilities like chat,
writing code, analyzing complex
text, doing your homework
for you, et cetera.
What's really
remarkable about this
is that this transition is
happening faster than we think.
So certainly, faster than
I thought at the beginning
of my PhD a few years ago.
So I think one really
apt analogy and the dates
actually match up in
an interesting way.
So in 1902, there are 130,000
working horses in Manhattan.
So these are horses
that you don't just
have around for giggles,
but you actually
have them because they
play some key role.
And they would-- these
horses would produce--
each would produce
pounds of manure a day,
times 130,000 horses, you
have a real manure problem.
So in fact, there were
entire conferences
that were just gathered
around the question
of-- entire academic
conferences around,
what do we do about all the
poop that these horses produce?
So in 1898, they actually
had one of these in New York.
And their conclusion
from that conference
was, there's nothing we can
do about the horse manure.
You just have to hold your
nose and deal with it.
10 years later, by 1912, cars
had already outnumbered horses
in Manhattan.
So that 10 year
transition, you saw
these things that have
been around for centuries
start to be replaced by cars.
And I think for us,
for language models,
for a lot of the
stuff that we do,
that 1912 moment was
probably last year.
So at least for me,
last year, I started
writing the majority of my code
using these language models.
Most people in my team do it.
I tell all my students
to do it, except when
they're doing their homework.
But this is a really
exciting transition
that we're living through.
One of these things that
is really driving this
is, a lot of the scale
is driven by GPUs.
So in a very real sense, you
could say GPUs are the new oil.
This is again a
older announcement,
but you're seeing hundreds
of billions of dollars
and more of
investment into GPUs.
History rhymes in interesting
ways with similar things,
but there are entire countries--
entire sovereign wealth funds
that are making these things
a major part of their piece.
And one thing that is
really abundantly clear
is that inference
is really the piece.
So you can think of inference
as the engine that turns
electricity into intelligence.
So the same way that oil is only
useful in a car, if you can have
an engine that turns that oil
into useful kinetic motion,
inference engines,
GPU kernels, these
are the things
that really turn--
that really turn
these GPUs from sand,
like Percy said, into something
that we can use today.
And I think that's clear.
So if you think about it,
these machine learning models,
they're really just
DAGs of operations.
There are some mathematical
object that exists in the ether.
The inference engines, the GPU
kernels, all these pieces, these
are the things that you
actually have to program
and map them down
to ML operations.
I think you do some
of that in this class.
I think you implement
some flash attention.
So some training side.
But there's a whole
world of complexity
when it comes to inference and
the inference side of things.
So if you take away
nothing from today's talk,
I hope there's one thing which
is, if you understand inference
and understand the
inference engines,
if you understand
the GPU kernels
that underlie a lot of
the core technology,
you can enable full stack
innovation in machine learning
algorithms.
So I'm going to start
with, in today's talk,
a high level overview of
the lifetime of a token.
So when you make a request
to one of these models, what
happens to that
request, how it goes
through the entire
inference service,
what are some of the interesting
choices you have to make.
And then I'll dive deeper into
two more research projects
around, if you take certain
pieces of this system, what
are questions that you
can ask and what are
some things that you can do?
Before I get into all
the technical details,
I'll quickly make a plug.
So I'm here representing
two organizations.
So one is UCSD, where
I have a small lab,
and some of their work is
represented in this talk.
Then I'm also
representing together
who did a bunch of the work
that's represented in this talk
together as an AI cloud.
So there's GPUs, Inference,
Fine-Tuning, and all the rest.
Heavy research background.
So including Percy, I don't
think you can see my mouse,
but he's on the screen.
And then we've got a big
research presence behind that,
and behind a lot of
the things that you're
going to see in this talk.
All right.
I'll start by giving
a high level overview
of a lifetime of a token.
So when you make a request
to a inference system,
what are the different pieces
that are going to go through?
And these slides are
cribbed from a presentation
that my student, Austin made
from his experiences together.
I'll make a note that
all of the slides
are completely AI generated
from Nano Banana Pro,
but they're pretty good
as long as you don't
look too closely at the tech.
So I'd say, at a high level
everything is correct.
If you look very closely, you'll
see things that are very wrong.
This is a overview of all the
pieces of an inference engine.
So I'll give a high level
description of how it works.
So you get a request in.
The first thing
that's going to happen
is that the request
gets scheduled
to various different GPUs.
You might have disaggregated
prefill and decode
on different machines.
You'll run that request
against a KV Cache to see,
have I seen this request or
versions of this request before?
Is there some compute
that I can actually save?
Then you'll start executing
the core machine learning code.
So here are new tokens.
Here are new operations
that we need to compute.
There are various optimizations
that you can make.
So you can split
that computation
across different machines.
You can parallelize
across different nodes.
You can parallelize it within
a node across different GPUs
depending on the
size of your model,
depending on how you can
split up, split that up.
And I think one of the exciting
things is that, as we are--
as the hardware is
developing, we're
actually going to start to see
more different choices that you
can make there.
But once you make all those
choices, once you execute
all the code at the end, you
get the tokens that you can say,
hey, Chad, what
did Percy mean when
he said linear
regression because I
skipped that day in my class?
And you get this whole
end to end experience.
One of the things
that I think is
useful to start
thinking about is,
what do these different
workloads look like?
And there's quite a bit
of different things.
So this is one of the sites
where if you look too closely,
I think some of the
fives turned into S's.
But one of the things that
you want to think about
is, when you're actually
serving production traffic,
it doesn't necessarily
look like-- certainly,
doesn't look what
the type of tokens
that you see during training.
But it also doesn't look like
if you just made up a traffic
workload in your head.
So what is the type thing
that we typically see?
So for a particular
workload, you'll
see a particular distribution
of input and output tokens.
So let's take a coding workload.
So let's say you're somebody
like Cursor, where you have
your whole code base is
available to the agent
and you're asking
questions about it,
typically, what
that will look like,
is that you'll have a
long amount of input.
So tens of Thousands
of input tokens.
And then depending on how
you've trained your model,
the model might output some
amount of thinking tokens,
or it might output
some short input in.
And this will change
based on workload.
It'll change based on model.
So a coding workload for
example will look very different
from a summarization workload,
or a narrative summarization.
So if your work involves pasting
entire books into a chat window
and then talking back and forth
to figure out what's happening,
that's going to look very
different than a standard chat
thing.
So if you just go
to chat and say,
hey, explain to me first
order calculus or whatever,
that's going to have very
different workload shapes.
The way that we use
language models today,
there's very turn-based
agentic workflows.
So when you're coding, you go
back and forth with your coding
agent, say, hey, do this.
No, I didn't mean that, do that.
Your coding agents themselves
can iterate on the language
models quite a bit.
So they might invoke
some tools and say,
grep search for something in
my data-- in my code base,
and then take that and go
feed it back to the model.
I might try to do an internet
search and look up this thing
that my user asked me.
So typically, you have
these multiple turns
in your conversation.
Now, another
interesting piece is
different applications
will have different times.
So if you're in a fast,
interactive chat based loop,
or if you're talking
on your phone
to ChatGPT in the
voice mode, you
might have relatively
quick responses.
If on the other hand, you've
put together an agentic workflow
where you say, hey,
go do this for me,
I'm going to leave you alone
and just iterate on your own,
you'll have a different cadence.
If at some point your agent
gets stuck and say, hey, help,
I need to ask for advice,
and you don't notice it,
there might be another
gap between turns.
So all of these
things start to define
what your workload looks like.
So how many new tokens do
you get in it every time?
How many tokens are
you going to generate?
How long is my session?
Am I a very sticky
user who keeps
going back and forth
with my Claude Agent,
or am I a user who's just
going to ask one question
and then leave and
come back the next day?
And of course, how long
between turns do you have?
I, for example, have
a chat that I've
had with a ChatGPT agent about
how I should set up my workout
and my workouts week to week.
And I interact with that
chat once every other week.
So that is a very
different traffic pattern
than some of the other ones.
And then of course, depending
on your application,
you might have
different targets.
So if you have a interactive
application, you might say,
I want to get the first tokens
back in less than a second,
so that the agent can
say, hey, I'm thinking
and I'm going to say
blah de blah de blah.
Or I might say, I know I'm going
to be generating 500 tokens,
and I want that whole
response to come back
within a certain amount of time
so that my user can read it fast
enough and all these pieces.
So as that-- when
that request comes in,
there are a few basic
pieces that come in.
I'll rest a bit on the
prefill and decode piece
in a little bit.
So let's say you have some
amount of text that comes in,
the first thing
you're going to do
is you're going to tokenize it.
I think you're all
familiar with that.
But then once there, you start
getting into a somewhat complex
scheduling regime because you
have to ask questions like,
have I seen these tokens before?
Can I just look up some of
the activations in a cache?
And then you get to basically,
these two major pieces
of the actual machine
learning computation.
These are called
prefill and decode,
and they're very
different beasts.
So prefill means let's say
you have 10,000 tokens that
you've never seen before, and
you want to go compute what
the activations and what
the logit should be.
So 10,000 tokens
in, one token out.
That's a very compute
bound operation.
So that actually looks
pretty close to the things
that you guys have been
looking at for training time.
So when you're training,
you have some large amount
of tokens.
You write your flash
attention kernel
when you run your training loop.
Prefill is very similar.
You just don't run
your backwards pass.
And then you have this
thing called decode.
So decode is when you're
then just generating
one token at a time.
So you pass in
these 10,000 tokens.
It's like, hey,
here's my code base,
tell me what function ABC does?
The model is going to
process the whole prompt
and then start generating
one token at a time, maybe
three or four tokens if you have
speculative decoding working.
And if you think about that
operation-- so every time you
generate a new token, you
then have to run that back
through the model.
If you do the math on that,
there's actually not too many
flops that you need to compute.
So it's going to be a
relatively light computation,
but it's going to be very
memory bandwidth bound.
So what that means
is you're going
to be running-- you have
to load up the model
every time just to
generate a single token.
At the end, you get--
at the end of that
model pass, of course,
you then have a
single number that
represents a token that then
gets turned into a string.
You probably do a little
bit of processing on that.
So you look for stop tokens.
You check.
You might run a safety
check to say, oh,
is my user trying to
hack into the system
in a bad way, et cetera?
And then at the end,
you get the tokens.
And the inference engine is
really running in this loop,
waiting for these
requests to come in.
So it's waiting-- so it's
running this scheduling
execution token sampling
loop and repeating.
So I'll get into a
little bit of-- so now we
can take one step deeper
and start to look at,
what does it look
like when you have
a system that is processing many
different requests at a time?
So we have this phenomenon
called-- this technique called
continuous batching.
So the way to read
this figure is that it
is time is flowing downward.
So as you go down, there are
new requests that are coming in.
So let's say, if
we go to step one,
you have some long requests.
You have a user that is asking
to analyze some long document,
and the engine is going and
generating a bunch of tokens
out.
You might have another
request comes in that starts
to take up some resources.
So these resources are
first compute resources.
You have to run things over
multiple requests at once.
They can be memory resources if
you're filling up a KB Cache.
And so you'll see
these multiple requests
happening at the same time.
After a step, that short
request might finish
and you get a new
request that comes in,
and maybe it's running
for a couple steps.
If you have another
request that comes in,
maybe it's another
very long request.
So that's going to be that
orange one in step four.
But maybe you don't
have enough GPU memory.
So you need to store all
your KV Cache on your GPU.
Maybe you've run out.
You might start queuing
for some reason there.
Then once that long
request is done,
you can start the new
request, and then, et cetera,
you can watch it run.
So already, you're seeing
some of the complexity
when you have many different
requests living in a system
and how it goes on.
One of the pieces
that's quite important
is this thing called a KV Cache.
So the way to think about
this is that you probably
have a lot of users who
are saying, hi, ChatGPT
or hi, Claude.
And then theoretically,
you don't
need to compute new
activations and run that again
for every single user.
Or if you have a long book
that the user has passed in,
you compute, you run the
prefill over that once,
and then the next time you get
some addendum to that request.
The next turn in
the conversation,
you don't need to compute
the whole thing again.
So we have these
mechanisms called KC Caches
that use prefix
sharing, that say, hey,
I have this new set of
tokens that comes in,
use a very traditional data
structure like a basic tree,
look at which tokens have I seen
before, which tokens are new,
and then basically, do a lookup
of what those activations are
going to look like.
Once you actually have the
computation on the GPUs,
there's various
ways to split it.
So I'm not sure if you
talked about this too much,
but let's say you have a
trillion parameter model
and you're running
on 280 gigabyte GPUs,
you're not going
to be able to fit
the whole model onto each GPU.
So there are various ways
that you might split it.
So you might take
every tensor and split
it four ways across four GPUs.
This is called
tensor parallelism.
Or today, we have a lot of
the state of the art models
or a mixture of experts models.
So you have these
individual experts
that get selectively activated
depending on different tokens.
You can split those
across different GPUs.
The choices that you
make at this point
will determine what
are the bottlenecks.
How many GPUs do you
need to run your model?
How many sessions can you
serve at the same time?
Et cetera.
One of the big
things that happens
is that we tend to split prefill
and decode onto different GPUs,
different sets of
machines, and that's
because they have very
different compute bottlenecks
and compute characteristics.
So prefill looks a lot like what
you guys do during training.
You just run it.
It's very flop heavy.
You can really use the
most out of your GPUs.
Decode on the other hand is
very memory bandwidth heavy.
Because you're not
doing that much compute,
but you still have to
load up all the model
weights at the same time.
These things will also take
different amounts of time.
So prefill will typically take a
lot longer than a single decode
step.
But you're going to be running
a lot more decode steps,
because you will run
prefill once for a prompt,
you'll run decode once for
every token that you generate.
So a very basic optimization
that pretty much we've
all started adopting
is that you'll
run prefill on one
set of workers,
decode on another
so that you can
specialize those two
computations to different
pieces of the stack.
And turns out, there's
a lot of innovation
that you can have when
you have these splits.
Some things that you
might have heard of,
that when NVIDIA bought Grok.
So NVIDIA, the King of GPUs,
buys this new inference chip.
One of the reasons is
that the decode workload
is so different from
prefill workload,
that if you're looking
at code, you can
be using very different chips.
So for example, in the next
generation of hardware,
NVIDIA is planning on using
its GPUs for the pre-fill side,
using these LPU Grok
chips for the decode.
You see similar
things with Cerebras.
So OpenAI has this compute
partnership with Cerebras.
It's another chip that's
much better at decode.
There are other
companies like SambaNova
and so on, that are
also making bets
on various parts of this space.
Here's a fun one,
an interesting one.
So when you actually
start deploying
these inference
engines at scale,
so when you're starting to serve
trillions of tokens or more
a day, you start to get
some pretty nasty bugs.
So this is a set of bugs.
I think most of
these happened in
late last year with some of the
open source inference engines.
And basically, one of
the characteristics
of these large scale
systems is that something
that will work well
at a small scale
will inevitably start
breaking at a large scale.
So we're talking events that
happen with 0.001% of the time
or less.
Some of these can be so NaN.
So sometimes,
you'll have a kernel
that is very slightly wrong.
But the conditions for
triggering it are very rare.
And you will start having
some of your logits
turn into NaNs halfway
through the computation.
When that happens,
we figure it out
that the model starts
outputting the same token.
So I think some
model, the output just
started saying, hi, hi,
hi, hi, after a while,
or start outputting
exclamation points
and you get caught
into these loops.
Another model, at
some point, someone
made a change to how
you're handling tool calls.
So tool calls are
when the model says,
hey, I want to make an internet
search or something like that.
So the model will actually
say, go do an internet search.
And then your end harness has to
then go use old fashioned code
to do the internet search.
At some point, those tool calls
stop being processed correctly
in one of the engines.
And the symptom for that the
completion lengths shot up
because the model would say,
hey, make an internet search,
and then it would usually--
when the model is
behaving correctly,
it says, hey, make
an internet search.
I'm done.
Go return to the user.
Go do that, whatever.
But in this case, it
wasn't returning correctly.
So it'd say, hey, make
an internet search.
Hey, make an internet search.
Hey, I don't know why there's
no internet search going on.
It would just get into
this very long doom
loop for tens of
thousands of tokens.
There's another one that--
this one was interesting
because it actually
took out a number of insurance
providers at the same time.
And it actually got blamed
on a quantization issue.
But actually, what was happening
was a much more subtle bug
where the model would
just suddenly, randomly
start to output
Chinese characters
when it had no reason to.
So for some models,
that sometimes there's
some speculation,
oh, they must have
fine-tuned on a Chinese model
because my model suddenly
starts.
I ask it a question
in English and starts
speaking back to me in Chinese.
Actually, what was happening is
that there was just an off by I
error in one of the kernels, and
it would be a very subtle bug.
So sometimes, you would read in
some extra uninitialized memory
space from your GPU, run it
through retention, and then
at the end of that
whole process,
you get a random
Chinese character.
Then the model will go,
why did I start suddenly
thinking in Chinese?
I must be-- the user must be
asking me a question in Chinese,
and then it will just go
veer off into Chinese.
So sometimes when
this happens, it's
because the model
has legitimately
been trained to say--
to think in Chinese.
Sometimes, it can just be an off
by one bug in somebody's code.
Some interesting things
that are starting
to happen in a lot of the more
advanced inference stacks.
So a major piece of running
large production systems
is that you want to have as
large of a KV Cache as possible.
So it is best if you
can cache requests
from many different users
or from the same user
across many different
sessions, and be able to run
as many sessions as possible.
You first started this by
storing your KV Cache on GPU,
and then you quickly
run out of GPU memory.
So the next, you can start
storing into CPU DRAM.
So if you're paying attention
to Jensen's keynotes,
he's recently started
getting very obsessed
with CPU performance.
One of the reasons is because
a past generation of CPUs
was actually really slow.
And as a result, started
bottlenecking a bunch
of very important workloads.
And as a result, you
start to pay attention
because if you're $500,000
machine is being bottlenecked
by the $1,000 CPU that you
purchased to put on top of it,
that's not a great place.
One of the reasons
that can happen
is that you might be storing
your KV Cache on CPU memory.
And so you really
care about the speed
of being able to read
that KV cache back.
Next, you might put more KV
cache onto the disk itself.
And then you start caring
about SSDs and SSD space.
Again, you've probably heard
these rumblings about OpenAI
buying up all the SSD,
all the DRAM in the world.
Part of the reason is
for stuff like this,
where you want to store as
much stuff in your KV Cache
as you can.
And then of course, when you're
actually building your engine,
there's this
complicated dance of,
I haven't seen these
tokens in a while.
Maybe I'll evict it,
send it on to the CPU,
or send it into disk, or send
it into some other global store.
When I get a new request
in, I have to go look.
I have to go wait
for those to come in,
fetch them, load them up into
my thing, and then we're happy.
It's kind of CPU offloading.
Is it like a special kind of
workload that gets offloaded?
For something fast, you
don't want to do this.
Time to hit a SSD is very long.
Can you repeat the question?
Yes.
Yeah, so the question is
so for this offloading,
is it a particular type of
workload that you offload?
So here, we actually
get to some pretty--
i'm sure none of you guys have
taken an operating systems
class.
But you should take your
operating systems classes--
you actually get to some pretty
classic scheduling things.
So you could have this
diagram except for the GPU
things on the right.
Looks exactly like a operating
systems diagram that you might
have seen in the
'70s or the '80s.
Because we used to have this
problem, where if you opened up
too many applications
on your computer,
you would run out of
CPU memory, and then
you'd have to put those
applications onto the disk.
And it is exactly
the same workload.
So ideally, here,
actually on the left side,
the Nano Banana
hallucinated evictions
for least recently
used which is actually
a pretty decent heuristic.
There's probably some OS paper
somewhere that says that LRU is
within 2x of what you can do.
That's optimal.
Of course, the best
thing that you want to do
is, if you could predict
the future, you would know,
oh, I'm about to have a request
come in of a particular kind.
Let me go prefetch
that memory in.
It might actually be possible
to predict the future.
So for example, when you
go into your chat app
and you bring up some old
conversation from a month ago,
that's a very strong
signal that you're
going to go start asking
a question about it.
You might then want to go
load that up onto a GPU.
But in a perfect world,
you predict the future.
If you can't predict the future,
you use various heuristics.
And really, it's a question
of how much traffic
you want to put onto
your GPU footprint.
I've never talked to
anybody who wants to put
less traffic onto their GPUs.
So I think Modulo or
subject to those SLAs
that we splashed up
at the beginning,
you want to serve as
much traffic as you can.
Some fun things that
are starting to happen.
So in the last generation
of Blackwell GPUs,
NVIDIA started putting
together these new GPUs called
NVl72 Grace Blackwell chips.
So these are 72 GPUs
that are connected
with really fast interconnects.
And so you start
to do things like,
how can I split my trillion
parameter model across all 72
GPUs?
Does this make any sense?
What does it buy me?
What happens?
How do I start to think
about fault tolerance?
So these things can fail a lot
for various different reasons.
One reason is that the
connectors are flimsy.
They're made of plastic,
not made of metal.
So if you like jam
the thing in too much,
then your cables are going to
bend the things a little bit,
and then you get really
flaky NV links, which
is a whole thing in itself.
But what happens when--
so this is the AI generation.
So let's put a fan into the
chips, which doesn't quite
make sense.
One of the things that you
want to start thinking about
is, if I've taken a model
split it across 64 GPUs,
and I'm serving production
traffic against millions
of users, trillions of tokens.
What do I do when a
single GPU goes down?
Is there some way to
make that fault tolerant?
And there's a lot of fun
things to think about there.
And then, of course,
you're starting
to see these models have a
million contexts or more.
How do you actually process it?
Do you split that context
across many different GPUs?
How do you do these
different things?
So I want to dive--
just very briefly
highlight one set--
one example of an
optimization that you
can start to make
when you start looking
at this whole process
from a systems level.
So this is a piece of
work that we put together
a few months ago called
Cache-aware Prefill-decode
Disaggregation.
It's a very simple optimization.
It's two lines of code
in the routing layer,
but can actually make a
pretty big difference.
So the basic idea is, you
have all these requests that
are coming in.
Most of them are going to
be turn by turn requests
in a conversation,
where somebody's already
started a conversation.
But let's say your average
conversation lasts 10 turns
and then the user goes
away, that suggests
that 10% of your requests are
going to be very fresh, very
new requests.
So when you have a new
request that comes in,
that's going to be
thousands of tokens.
It's going to look
very different.
It's going to be a lot
more expensive to compute.
You don't necessarily
want to put that prefill
against a short conversation
where you're halfway
through conversation.
So someone paste
in a book and says,
hey, talk to me about this book.
You don't want that
running at the same time
as someone who's midway
through a conversation,
like, chat explain to me
why 1 plus 1 equals 2.
And chat is like,
1 plus 1 equals 2
because numbers and whatnot.
And you're like,
oh, I don't get it.
You don't want that very
short question and answering
to happen in the same
time, on the same GPUs,
as the very long request.
So you can put together this
really simple router that
says, OK, if we have
a new request that
comes in that's very
low cache hit rate,
send it to one set of
GPUs so that those can all
process things together and then
send all my other warm requests
to another set of prefill nodes.
It turns out if you do
this, you can get up
to 40% faster serving with these
very, very simple optimization.
So that's one set
of things I'd say,
the way that I
would characterize
where we are in
terms of the research
and these techniques is
that we're very early.
So this is the type of
thing that in 10, 20 years,
they're going to look back
on and be like, oh, why are
these guys talking about this?
Isn't this already
obvious to folks?
But really, it's because we're
starting to see these things,
running them at
production in new ways.
Seeing these new bits
of traffic in new ways.
All right.
So that was a overview of the
inference life of a kernel.
Now I'm going to talk about
two interesting research
projects that are very much
inspired by some of the things
that we see when serving things.
So this first one we're going to
be talking about language model
decode, and how
you can make it go
a lot faster with these
things called mega kernels.
This is a collaboration
between Stanford and Together.
So the fundamental challenge
when you're running Decode.
So Decode is the process by,
you've processed your prompt
and now you're generating
one token at a time.
The fundamental
challenge is that you
have to run the whole model
to generate a single token.
So that means that instead of
using all this big parallelism
that you get with
a GPU that you can
do during pre-filler
training, you've
now turned this massively
parallel system into basically
a glorified memory loader.
And one of the things that
makes this extra challenging
is that the way
that we typically
write down kernels
and run a model
is that we will write
down kernels and program
things one operation at a time.
So you guys can probably
understand why this is so.
Kernels tend to be pretty
challenging to write.
I'm sure you guys all had a lot
of fun writing flash attention.
But that means that
typically, what we do is
we look at all the different
operations in a language model,
and we will run--
we will write a single kernel
for that operation at a time.
So this makes things a
lot easier to program
because you just have
to write your Norm
kernel, your matmul kernel,
your attention kernel.
But you end up seeing, it ends
up introducing a lot of downtime
into your system.
So this is an example
of what it might
look like when you're running
inference across your kernel.
So this is obviously a
cartoon, but the example
is drawn from a particular
attention inference kernel.
The way to read this is that
on the x-axis, you have time.
So time is flowing
from left to right.
On the y-axis, you have all
the different little streaming
multiprocessors on your GPU.
So on a H100, there
are 132 of these.
On the B200, there's
148, et cetera.
The bars indicate useful work.
So when there's a bar here, one
of the processors on the GPU
is actually doing work, and the
empty space is just waiting.
So you're just waiting
for other operations
to finish so that you can
have something else go on.
And so basically, you
get into this position
where no matter how well
you try to write the kernel,
you're always going to
have downtime in your GPU.
So you're going to have
things like kernel launch.
So a kernel lock
or kernel teardown,
that's these big gaps in
the red and the yellow.
You're going to have these
things called tail effects.
So this is just the
same way that if you
have a short prompt that gets
processed with a very long
prompt, this same thing
goes all the way down
to the basic
attention operation.
If you're processing
a batch of inputs
and one input is very short,
one input is very long,
you're going to be waiting for
the very long input to finish.
And then because you're running
these across multiple kernels,
you will actually start to see
these gaps between kernels start
to add up.
So one thing that we put
together to try to solve this,
is thing called a Megakernels.
So this is basically
saying instead
of treating each operation in
the model as its own operation
writing kernel for it, instead,
let's write a single kernel
to cover multiple
operations at once.
This is similar to the fusion
that you see in flash attention,
except done more
aggressively across a larger
number of things.
And in particular,
what it does is
it turns a GPU from
a single device--
a single operation is you
start thinking of the GPU
as a massive distributed
system and saying,
OK, I have all this work
that I need to get done.
Some of it has dependencies
on other stuff.
So that red stuff
has some dependencies
on some of the green bars.
How can I schedule it?
How can I distribute the work
to maximize my GPU utilization?
If you do this just to the
attention inference kernel,
you get 30% to 70% speedups.
And then the nice thing
is that you can actually
do this to the whole model.
So this is one layer
of a Llama-1B model.
So here, we've basically
taken the entire layer
and put it together
into one kernel.
If you look at all
these different bars,
you see things are overlapped
in really weird ways.
That's because we are now
starting to overlap a weight
load from the next-- from
the layer into the attention,
or starting to run
parts of reduction
before the attention
operation is over.
Here's one interesting example.
So here's one thing
that you can do.
So if you look at modern LLMs,
you have the attention layer.
You have the QKV projections.
You're going to add
some rope scaling to it.
So that's these blue lines.
So those blue lines
are QKV plus rope.
And then the orange
lines, this is
the beginning of the attention.
So one of the insights is that
you can start loading in your KV
Cache into your attention
before you're finished with QKV,
and particularly, during decode.
So these orange bars with
some of these circles,
you start the KV Cache load
while the QKV plus rope is still
running.
And then once QKV is done, then
you have your new query tokens.
You can run the rest of
the attention operation.
So basically, when you have this
fine-grained control of GPUs,
you can start some operations
before others are over.
Here's another one.
So again, the orange
is the first part
of the attention computation.
The red is the O projection
that comes after attention.
And you have your O projection.
Start loading the weights
before your attention operation
is over.
We put this together in a
very relatively complex CUDA
framework with basically
instruction and instruction
based abstraction,
where we can implement
each sub-kernel in
its own file, and then
have a big virtualized
shared memory
system to orchestrate the
running of these operations.
And to do this, we put
together this library
called ThunderKittens, which
is one of these kernel writing
libraries.
You can think of it
as almost like Triton,
except more low
level, a lot more
fine-grained
control over things.
The payoff is you get near speed
of light decoding inference.
So these numbers are
actually a lot better now.
But the Megakernel shown
by this bar in teal,
and you can see it runs
a lot faster than some
of the other state
of the art engines.
And on the H100,
it's achieving 72%
bandwidth utilization, which
is near the speed of light
on the GPU.
So if you just ignore all the
complexities of what we're
doing here and say, how
fast can the GPU physically
go to do this operation?
We are pretty close to 72%
of that speed of light.
So one interesting bit there is
a takeaway from that section,
is that, if you have very
deep control of the kernels
and the understanding
of the hardware,
you can start to enable very
different compute paradigms.
And all these
things, you only see
when you start playing with
inference at a deep level.
And now, I'll talk
about something
that's a little bit new.
So this is now getting into
the realm of new architectures.
And I'm going to be talking
about this new model called
Parcae.
So this is some
work that comes out
of my UCSD lab led
by Hayden, and then
also in collaboration with these
two folks, Zachary and Taylor.
So I'm going to
come back to this.
So at the beginning of the
talk, I talked about, hey,
all these new
capabilities are coming
because you're starting to scale
these models, and parameters,
and data.
With Parcae, we wanted to
ask another question, which
is, is this the only
way you have to scale?
Or is it potentially is
there potentially something
else-- some other way that
you can get this quality?
And with Parcae, we wanted
to-- this was basically
our take on a technique
called loop transformers,
where you take some
blocks of your transformer
and you run them in a loop.
So instead of having
your tokens go all one
layer at a time
through the model,
at some point you say, hey,
as you're going through,
just send it back through
that loop at a time.
You're going to see, there's a
couple different pieces here.
So one is, we use some State
Space Model theory, some SSM
theory to stabilize
this operation.
Naively, if you just run
this and let the thing train,
we saw that the thing
was going to blow up.
And then the other
thing is we started
to see some interesting scaling
laws that suggest that you want
to be scaling the recurrence
of these recurrent models
as you increase the data.
So in order to make the best
use out of your parameters,
you want to actually be
reusing them somewhat.
First, I'll talk a
little bit of motivation
of why we found this looping
problem to be very interesting.
So the basic idea is, let's say
you have some activation that's
going through part of
your model, at some point,
it hits these loops
blocks and it's just going
to run the same activation.
It's going to run through that
same layer some number of times.
So that purple block
is the recurrent block.
And then at the end, you get
the thing that comes back.
So there are some
advantages of this.
So you can keep your
parameters constant,
but it gives you a dial
to increase your flops.
So if you think that
flops-- more flops
equals higher
quality, this is a way
to increase your quality without
paying a higher parameter cost.
Another thing is,
there's this old work--
old is a relative term
from a few years ago--
that suggests that you actually
get higher expressivity--
their expressivity.
There are things that
you can't express
with the same number
of parameters,
that you can express
with these looped models.
And one of our driving
questions was, what's
the best quality per parameter?
What's the best
intelligence per parameter?
Or intelligence per
parameter and data
that these things
will allow you to do?
There are some promising
initial results.
So this is a paper from Tom
Goldstein's group in Maryland
that suggests that hey,
this thing might be better
than transformers.
These are some results
on the Arc tasks.
And there's also a
bunch of Twitter hype,
because about a week
before we released Parcae,
some dude from OpenAI said that
Claude mythos is a recurrent--
is a looped language model.
I don't think it's right.
I think he was
just making it up.
But as a result, it
really blew up in Twitter
in speculation
right before this.
Eventually, he had to write
this blog post being like, hey,
my bad, I just made that up.
None of it's true.
But it was sufficiently
interesting to go.
So we were working on it
before this Twitter hype,
but I think there was something
interesting, something
interesting to look at here.
Now, one problem with
these looped models
is if you looked at any of them
and you tried to train them,
and then you changed anything
about the training algorithm
at all.
So if you change the learning
rate by a little bit,
you'd suddenly start to
see these models blow up.
So if you did a simple thing
like a learning rate sweep,
you'd see nine times out
of 10, this model just
isn't going to converge,
it's going to blow up.
You're going to get NaNs.
You're going to get
these big loss spikes.
And so we were
saying, hey, there
seems to be something
wrong with this.
So if you're training a model
and you're actually scaling it
up, and you see there,
these big loss spikes, that
suggests something has gone
very wrong with your training
process, you should
take a deeper look
and try to figure
out what happened.
In previous work,
there were some hacks
like you can put
norms in every layer
to figure out what's
happening or just pick two--
the learning rate of 2e-4.
Don't pick any of the
other learning rates.
But we were thinking, hey, the
existence of these loss spikes
suggests that there's probably
something more deeper going on.
And so we took a bit of a
mathematical state space
model-esque approach to
the stabilization question.
Our basic insight was, you
can look at this process.
So actually, if you
look at this process,
you try to think about how
to analyze it analytically.
It's going to be very
complicated, because this big R
block has tons of parameters.
There's all sorts
of nonlinearities.
There's a Softmax,
there's GELU, and RoPE,
and all these other things.
So if you try to
analyze it analytically,
it's quite complex.
Our insight was, we
were just saying,
OK, let's actually just look
at the residual of this thing.
So how is this activation
changing from block to block?
Our first empirical
observation was hey,
it actually doesn't
change that much.
So each of these
residual blocks is
changing the vector
a little bit,
but not really having
a massive impact.
And as a result, how
can we-- so maybe
we can actually model this.
Maybe we can actually look at
what's happening more deeply.
And so what we did is we went
and wrote down a dynamic system
over this residual.
And when we did, we realized
there's a couple pieces in here
that when you look at how
you write down the model,
might look relatively
benign, but actually
end up being a huge bit.
So what we did was we said,
OK, there's all this nonlinear
stuff, there's this
attention, there's this GELU,
there's this big
feed-forward network
with the intermediates
and stuff,
we're going to all
put that into a box.
We're just going to
call that R. And this R
is going to be some
big nonlinear thing.
But we're going to put it--
just take it to the side.
What you're left with is
these A and B matrices.
So this B matrix is
some transformation
over your initial vector.
So what is that first vector
before you start the loop?
And then this A vector is-- this
A matrix is how do you transform
that residual in each loop?
And what we did is we said, hey,
this simple thing, if you take
all the complexity
of the transformer,
stick it to the side, you
have a relatively simple way
of looking at all the
previous loop transformers.
And in previous
cases, you do end up
making some pretty
normal decisions.
So in one case you
just say, oh, you just
treat it as the identity.
You're just going to add things.
In another case, it's a
fully learnable matrix.
And then we said, OK, what
happens if we just so--
the residual-- we
observed empirically,
that these A and B matrices
are actually dominating
the magnitude of this equation.
What happens if you just drop
that complicated nonlinear
piece?
What do you get out?
Well, you get out actually
a pretty simple system
that if you use high
school calculus,
you can just solve
it to figure out what
the answers are going to be.
So here's the closed
form solution.
You can actually
compute what is,
given what the
initial activation is,
and what that
initial injection is,
you can actually just
empirically compute
what the activation is going
to look like at Step T plus 1.
And you notice a
couple of things.
So this thing is dominated
by these A matrices.
And especially, this A matrix
that you are powering up
to a large degree.
And from here,
what we realize is
that there's this quantity
called the spectral radius
of this A. So spectral
radius is basically
like another word for norm.
One way that you
can look at this
is that, you're
taking this matrix.
You're powering it
up to huge amounts.
If this matrix can learn
to be something like--
let's say that this matrix--
if you go to scalars, imagine
that this matrix is 2.
And then this T is
like 16 or something,
you've now taken
this activation,
you've blown it up to
2 to the power of 16.
And it's really big.
And this starts to explain
some of those big loss spikes.
And in particular, what we found
is that, the choices that you
make for these A and
B matrices that people
have made in these previous
papers are either--
we call them, marginally
stable or unstable.
Unstable-- make the
system unstable.
And so with Parcae
we said, OK, well, we
figured out this thing where if
you take this particular look
at it, and you let these A
and B do whatever they want,
you're going to get things
that really explode.
What if we just constrain A and
B such that if you run the math
they're not going to explode?
So for A, what we
did is we said,
OK, we're effectively
going to make
that A matrix a negative
diagonal matrix.
So if you power that up, the
term eventually goes to zero,
so it doesn't blow up.
This B matrix,
we're going to put
a-- stick a really simple
linear norm against it,
because this B matrix actually,
only gets applied once
and doesn't really blow up.
E can be the spectral radius.
It's now going to
be less than 1.
It's now actually going
to be a stable system.
And now if you go train
this model, what we saw
is that you actually
saw stable loss curve.
So Parcae is this stabilized
thing where we re-parameterize
A and B. You can see that even
with this the 6e-4 learning rate
that was so bad for
the other models,
you actually got a
stable model at the end.
And you see that
with doing this,
you can naturally constrain the
state norm of the activations.
So two pieces here.
So that orange baseline is
just a completely unconstrained
model.
You can see it blows up,
goes to 10 to the 19th.
This blue line is
actually a model where
you are applying a norm to it.
So what happens here is
that the model is actually
trying to expand the
activations because it's saying,
oh, with more room, I can
represent different things
better.
I can put these different
concepts further away
from each other or whatnot.
And then you're
applying norm to it
to take that big thing
that's trying to expand.
Then you try to norm
it back down to one.
And then you have this big--
these two pressures that are
fighting against each other that
manifests in loss spikes.
So even though on the right,
your norms are very good,
you're not seeing the
activation actually blow up.
You do see that the loss can
do some pretty gnarly things.
So basically, there's
this pretty simple change
in the activations can
stabilize the training,
stabilize these recurrent loops.
So it's not only a
more stable system,
you actually also get more
higher quality models.
So this is a table where we
are comparing Parcae models
against a previous loop
transformer called Recurrent
Depth Model.
So you can see
higher performance
across a variety
of applications.
So you see Parcae outperforms
the previous models
and also outperforms strong
transformer baseline.
So this transformer is one
of the nanochannel ones where
a bunch of people are
trying to just get
it to learn as fast as it can.
And these Parcae models, if you
take that same basic transformer
architecture, start looping
it, and then stabilize it,
you get better
perplexities, better end
to end quality as well.
And then one-- and
then we started
to run some very basic
scaling laws here.
And here, our question was, OK,
this is really, really cute.
You can do this looping
thing to make things better.
But really, should you--
is there any evidence
that there's
something here that we
want to be doing looping
more aggressively?
So here, I'll take a step back.
A few years ago, there
was all this work
as we started to enter this
regime where you wanted
to scale up all these
models, a natural question
is, should I make
the models bigger
or should I just
train on more data?
So a few years
ago, folks started
to ask, how should I scale these
two quantities with each other?
Should I scale model parameters?
Should I scale data?
And we came up with all these
very complicated power law
curves that all look like this.
They're very pretty.
There's lots of colors.
What you want to look
out for is basically--
what you want to look out for
is, if that curve is going down
into the right, it
suggests you should
be scaling both data and
parameters at the same time.
If we were going
straight down, that
would mean just increase
your training data.
There's no need to
increase your parameters.
If it's going-- if it's
flat, just going straight
to the right, that means don't
increase your data at all,
just increase your parameters.
But you see, it's going
down into the right.
That means you should scale data
and parameters at the same time.
And now you see this.
You train a $1
trillion parameter
model on $35 trillion tokens,
and you get better quality.
So our question was, OK, where
does recurrence fit into this?
And there are a couple--
so down into the right means you
want to scale data in params--
there are a couple
possibilities with recurrence.
And so for example,
you might conclude,
you should never
run a recurrence.
It's better to just keep the
same single recurrent model.
You might conclude, you
should do a ton of recurrence,
or maybe only some
recurrence to the bit.
What we're showing here is, at
least in these initial scaling
laws, all of these
curves are isometric,
and ISO-param, ISO-FLOP.
So each of these
curves is a model.
So on the left
and the right, you
have the same number
of parameters.
As you go down, as
you change the colors,
we are increasing
the amount of flops
that you use to train
the model by increasing
the amount of data.
So here, we're varying
data and varying
the number of recurrences.
What we find is that in
both of these models,
you see this down into
the right trend again.
So what this is suggesting is
that for these fixed parameter
training things, as you
increase the amount of data,
you should actually also
be increasing the amount
of recurrences that you have.
We find that these recurrences
follow some pretty classic power
laws.
So you can actually
start to predict.
You can get these scaling laws
to start to predict quality,
as you scale, recurrences
and your tokens jointly.
Yeah.
For a fixed model size
[INAUDIBLE] recurrence.
What about jointly [INAUDIBLE]
scaling [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah.
So we have this really
complex 3D figure that showed
recurrences, and
data, and parameters.
And it pointed also whatever
down into the right,
and down that way
at the same time.
So if you believe
that figure, it
suggests you should be
scaling all three together.
But that figure was just really
hard to look at, because it was
3D and weird.
So these power laws suggest,
when you're increasing data
you should be
increasing recurrence.
And then you have other
power laws that suggest,
when you're increasing data you
should be increasing parameters.
So obviously, you
should increase--
well, it suggests that you
should increase all three
of them if you can.
But one piece here
is that if you're
going to fix your
model size and you're
going to increase
the amount of data,
you should also be increasing
the recurrence, which
is interesting because as far
as I know, all of our models
today have no
recurrence in them.
So they're all at the
very left of these curves.
And they all have a
ton of data, which
suggests that there might
be something slightly better
that we could be doing
when training these models.
And here's just that
experiment in another way.
So on the orange curve,
you have-- so here,
we fixed the model size.
The orange curve is
a fixed depth model.
So this is like a traditional
transformer model.
The blue curve is when
you fix the flop budget,
where do you hit on the
curve for a looping model?
So here, the orange
and blue dots
have been trained with
the same number of flops,
but a different amount of data,
but they're the same size.
When you get to
that number of flops
by increasing
recurrences as well as--
and not just
increasing data, you
start to get smaller validation
losses, which again suggests
it might be the case that
we should be looping all
of our big pre-training runs.
So that's Parcae.
If I take a little
step back and go back
to the big takeaway of the
talk, I think hopefully,
I've given you a
little sense today
of if you understand the
inference of these models,
if you understand
the GPU kernels,
you understand all the
pieces that goes into it.
You can really start to
enable full stack innovation
and machine learning algorithms.
So whether that's through a
new routing algorithm that
lets you serve
more traffic serve
traffic in a different way.
Or new kernels that allow you
to run part of your system way
faster.
Or new architectures
that say, if you
have a lot fewer
parameters, you can fit them
in a subset of your
GPUs in a different way,
reduce the amount
of communication,
these are all different
pieces of that question
of that research problem
that we're seeing today.
And yeah, hopefully I've
inspired at least one of you
in this room to go take a
deeper look at some of that.
So with that, thanks.
Happy to take a few questions.
[APPLAUSE]
We have about five, 10
minutes for questions.
So if you have a
question, raise your hand.
Parcae, are you training
from scratch on the loop?
I guess I was
wondering if you could
take a picture of [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah.
Great question.
So the question
was, with Parcae,
are we training from scratch?
Is there anything you can
do with pre-trained models?
So there was a really troll
blog post from someone
a few months ago where
it was like, hey, I
won some leaderboard competition
without training a single thing.
And what he did was he
actually looped a two or three
layers in a Quinn
model, and just
saw that on some math things it
started having higher quality.
So we have a little
bit of work trying
to look into this that
maybe coming out soon.
But there could be
some models where
if you do a little
bit of looping just
to the pre-trained model, you
can get a higher quality thing,
which is really weird.
It disturbs me.
I don't know why that
would possibly be the case.
But yeah, we'll be--
we're quite interested in this.
I think we'll be looking
at it and hopefully,
if I can convince
Hayden, he'll be
staring at the activations--
at the actual weights
to figure out why when you
loop it, it gets better.
Here's just a follow up on that.
So you talked about compute
optimality for the loop models,
can you speak about the
inference implications
and the memory and how that
can make you go faster?
Yeah.
So one of the reasons
that I was personally
very excited in
these loop things
is that, one of
the big bottlenecks
to serving inference
efficiently actually
ends up being GPU memory.
So if you have fewer
parameters, you
can fit, for example,
more KV Cache,
or you can do less
communication because you
need to split your model against
fewer GPUs and things like that.
So there's actually
a lot of flexibility
that a smaller
model will get you.
I also had this
dream that if you
could make the recurrent
block small enough,
you could actually write
a little Megakernel
to just do that recurrent
in a little very
fast Megakernel loop.
So far, we haven't been able to
make those blocks small enough.
But I think it's
quite interesting.
Certainly, with the next
generation of the LPU,
the Grok chips that are
coming with NVIDIA things.
Those have 250 megabytes of
memory or something like that.
So the thing that you'll
be able to fit into them
is very, very small.
But maybe you can design
something that will actually
fit into them, and then you can
just keep your weights in memory
the whole time and just run
your activations through
as quickly as you can.
So there are non-linear
benefits that you
can get if you can cross
some of these thresholds
that I'm hoping that we'll be
able to get to pretty soon.
Yeah, OK.
[INAUDIBLE] I'm curious.
I guess the trade offs
are that it's always
strictly more optimal.
[INAUDIBLE]
Great.
So the question is, what are
the trade offs for my kernels?
The trade offs are people's
blood, sweat, and tears.
So Megakernels, turns out
they're very, very labor
intensive to write.
So to give you some context, a
full talented kernel engineer
over the course of a
year, will probably
be able to write Megakernels
for one hardware for two
or three models for
batch sizes 1 to 16.
Go batch size 17, he was
like nope, start over.
Got to go again.
So they're very, very
challenging to write.
And together, we're
trying to put together
some compilers that can
automate some of that process.
But I'd say, it's a very
challenging thing to do.
I think the basic
Megakernel idea
has gone in peaks and troughs
over the last few decades
when it comes to
GPU programming.
But yeah, so if you can do
it, it will go super fast.
You will never be
able to go faster,
but it just takes a lot of
energy and a lot of effort.
Cool.
Maybe I can ask a question.
So can we talk a little
bit more about co-design?
And in particular, you
mentioned all these new hardware
like Grok and Cerebras
on the inference side.
So if you're designing
a model and that's
going to be the
serving platform,
how should you be changing
your architecture?
Yeah, I think there's
a couple of things
that you should look at.
So one is, you are going to
be most constrained by memory
first.
So if you know that you're
going to be taking a model
and serving it a
particular Cerebras chip,
you want to go look
at the Cerebras wafer,
and figure out how much
memory you have, and then
size your model so that it can
fit there with enough KV Cache
or whatever to spare.
If you look at carefully,
at the Chinese models that
are coming out, they've started
making some interesting choices
that suggest they
might be starting
to think about the Huawei
chips that are coming out.
You'll see quantization
choices that people make.
So if you have a
model that you're
intending to serve
on NVIDIA GPUs,
for example, NVIDIA's new
Nemotron model that they
released, you will train
that model in NVFP4.
This is a FP4 format that is
proprietary to NVIDIA chips.
If you're not going to run it
on NVIDIA chips, if you're AMD,
then you're going to run this
other format called MXFP4.
They each have
their pros and cons.
You'll make these subtle
choices based on the hardware
that you're choosing.
I think there was a
question over there.
I was wondering if it's
ever-- if you just care about
compute optimal training,
is it ever optimal to loop
as opposed to just
adding more parameters,
or is it mainly like a trick
to reduce inference cost?
Yeah.
So the trick with
compute optimal
is it is, usually, like
given a flop budget--
--repeat the question.
Oh yeah.
Sorry.
Yeah, the question
was for Parcae,
would you ever choose
to loop instead
of increasing parameters?
And so the trick
with compute optimal
is always given
some flop budget,
figure out what you want to hit.
It's almost a little bit
contrived in that sense,
because if you want a
higher quality model,
you should just increase
your FLOPs budget.
And if you decided on your
model size, just train longer.
Or if you're restricted by your
model size, then loop longer.
Or if you run out of data,
then pick the model size
that you think will
be as overtrained-- as
well trained as you
can for that size.
So I think there are choices.
And of course, you make all
these choices in the context of,
do I think it'll get picked up?
How am I going to serve it?
If you're going to
release the open source,
what is the size of model
that people can serve
like on your laptop today?
So I think all these choices
go into making a choice.
All these things go into making
a choice of how big a model
you choose to train.
I think if you just
make the model bigger
and train it on more data, it's
always going to get better.
But I think it really depends
on those design points.
Maybe another question
about co-design.
So you mentioned
at the beginning
different use cases like agentic
coding versus let's say batch
processing of data.
So what are the most
dramatic differences
in terms of optimal
architectures
that you see across
different use cases?
And at the end of
the day, of course
model developers has to
pick one and try to not be
reasonable on many use cases.
Yeah.
That's a great question.
So I think one of
the big differences--
so when you have these
agentic looped workflows,
one of the things
that matters a lot
is that you want to keep your
KV Cache as hot as possible.
So if you're doing a big batch
processing thing where you only
see each document once
and then you translate it,
the KV cache doesn't
necessarily matter as much.
If you look at something like
the DeepSeek MLA attention,
that is a radical
compression of the KV
cache compared to what you
would have for another model.
Or if you have the model that
can process its KV Cache in FPA
or FP4, those are
pretty big departures
in terms of the
size of the KV Cache
that if you are sensitive
to an agentic workflow
you would look at.
Then of course, the biggest
one is like causal attention
or non-causal attention.
So if you're just doing a big
batch processing workflows.
Like for the
longest time, Google
was just using Bert models.
I think probably still
uses Bert models on search.
And that's because
you don't really
need to be generating a bunch
of tokens on the other end.
So you just do that big
bidirectional attention once,
you get your vector
out, then you
stick that in database, do
whatever you will with it.
Whereas the chat workflows,
those processing,
there's always going to be
this decode portion of it.
I think there have been
intermediate things
like T5 was at some point
a choice that people made
to do some bidirectional
processing, and then also
some generation.
OK, maybe one last question.
Oh, yeah.
[INAUDIBLE], it was
about using everything
into one kernel,
[INAUDIBLE] but what
you were talking about before.
So I was just wondering,
how does that [INAUDIBLE]
work a communication
across multiple computers
are scaling the cost
of [INAUDIBLE] that.
Yeah, great question.
So the question is about,
how does Megakernel
work when you have multiple
GPUs communication in the loop?
We had some very early
preliminary work about this.
So it turns out you
can also fuse the NCCL
calls into the Megakernel
if you set it up correctly.
I think we haven't found
a really great killer use
case for that yet,
where sometimes you're
just bound by the latency
of the NCCL call itself.
So these are also pieces of
things that you can fuse.
When DeepSeek 4 came out,
the DeepSeek 4s released
a Megakernel for the mixture of
experts inference layer that can
run just for that where they
actually did fuse some of those
communication.
So I think what we
are starting to see,
we're starting to
see more of is,
as you get to more
of these models,
you'll have a little Megakernel
for a part for the computation,
but you won't necessarily have a
Megakernel for the whole model,
unless of course, you pay the
blood, sweat, and tears price
and then really, really
get the whole thing going.
OK, I think that's
all the time we have.
Let's thank, Dan again.
[APPLAUSE]
Thanks so much for having me.